<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A litell dialogue off [sic] the Consolator cõfortynge the Churche in hyr afflictions, taken out off [sic] the 129. psalme. / Composed in frẽche by M. Peter du Val. ; And translated into Englyshe by Robart Pownoll. Anno 1556 Mẽs Junij..</title>
            <author>DuVal, P. (Pierre)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07588</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 82474805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7376.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">82474805</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 82474805</idno>
            <idno type="VID">185137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2251:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A litell dialogue off [sic] the Consolator cõfortynge the Churche in hyr afflictions, taken out off [sic] the 129. psalme. / Composed in frẽche by M. Peter du Val. ; And translated into Englyshe by Robart Pownoll. Anno 1556 Mẽs Junij..</title>
                  <author>DuVal, P. (Pierre)</author>
                  <author>Pownall, Robert, 1520-1571.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Lambrecht?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno .1556. Mens .Junij .14..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imprint information from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸ E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: last leaf torn, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Massachusetts Historical Society.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:185137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A litell di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alogue off the Conſolator co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge the Churche in hyr afflictions, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out off the 129. pſalme. Compo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che by. M. Peter du Val. And tranſlated into Englyſhe by Robart Pownoll. Anno 1556. Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. Iunij.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Comforte them that are feable mynded, lyfte vp the weake, and be patient towardes all men. <bibl>1. Theſſa. 5.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte hym ſelfe, and God oure father (which hathe loved vs, and hathe gyven euerlaſtynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolation, and good hope through grace) comfort your hertes, &amp; ſtablyſhe you in all good ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge and doynge. <bibl>2. Theſſalo. 2.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Anno. 1556. Menſ. Iunij. 14.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_faithful">
            <pb facs="tcp:185137:2"/>
            <head>To the fayghtfull.</head>
            <p>FOR as myche as in all ages, the Lorde God (and that by his ſecret &amp; iuſte iudgment, and for certaine cauſes expreſſed vnto vs in his holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures) hathe alwayes expoſed and gyven ouer his people, to the ragynge rygoure, &amp; viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t affliction off the wycked: ſo that wordly wyſdom blynded, dothe eſteme the condition &amp; ſtate of the fayghtful moſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te vnfortunate. Beynge ſubiecte to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny myſeres, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned of men, deſtituted off ryches, afflicted by pouertye, aſſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted off tyrrantes, banyſhed out off theyre owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryes, theyre goodes confyſked, ſome tyme impriſoned, oftentymes mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered, drowned, buryed quycke, hedded, bornte, hanged, &amp; extemed no more then the fylthynes off the worlde, and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cowrynge off al thynges. And on the o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſyde ſeynge the wycked (gyuen ouer to all vngodlynes) proſper in felicite, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ounde in wealthe, increace in ryches, continewe in healthe, luſty in body, mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty in power, hauynge the worlde at they<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re wyll, in ſhuche ſorte that theyre condi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion in reſpect off the other, ys to be deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red: ſo that this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation dothe not a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell
<pb facs="tcp:185137:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
troble the ſimple mynded, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no thynge but that which they ſee pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſently before theyre eyes. Wherfor to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhuche a maſed baſhfulnes as now oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupyethe the myndes off a great manye of ſimple well dyſpoced people: and ſome what to elivate and ſtyre vp theyre decly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpiretes. I haue thought good to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medye the ſame by ſome lytell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation: the which amongeſt the offices off chari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te dothe not poceſſe the laſt place, &amp; ought never to be farre dyſtant from the feloſhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe off the fayghtfull. For as callamites and troubles ſhall never fayle them this worlde: even ſo behouethe it them to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all wayes in theyre hande, in theyre mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the, and in theyre herte, godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, which at this preſent ys moſt neceſſary vnto the chyldryne off God, yff euer it were requyſite: ſeynge that tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations do now abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with out meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re more then in tymes paſte. For in theſſe dayes whether ſo euer the fayghtfull go, or torne them ſelves: eyther the fyres are redy kendled to conſume them, or the pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons &amp; dongions are open to reſſayve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or els theyre howſes &amp; goodes are ſealed vp by the feales off vniuſte iuſtices to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueryſhe them, or els they fleinge hyther
<pb facs="tcp:185137:3"/>
&amp; thyther as poore ſlaves &amp; vacabondes, deſtitute bothe off mony &amp; fryndds do ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer infinite miſeres &amp; pouertyes, and are compelled to ſupporte a thowſand oppro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres &amp; iniures, as people forſaken &amp; vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vnworthy off all goodnes. With out omittynge, that they are compaſſed abou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te with an innumerable multitude off ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſaries: amongeſt whom on the one ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de are thoſſe great and ferefull giantes with theire rable of grevous greſhoppers, to wytt, the Pope, his Lardenales, Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chebiſhopes, Byſhoppes, Myters, Croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, Croiſſyers, thounderynge &amp; rorynge with theyre titeles, Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctiſſimi, Cole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi, Reuerendiſſimi, Obſeruandiſſimi: and about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are theyre Prothenotares Archedeacons, Chanones, Curates and Preſtes, with an infinite no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes &amp; fryers: all to gyther animated &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flambed to warre agaynſte the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, &amp; ferynge God. On the other ſyde are armed the Ceaſars inuictiſſimi, the Rynges illuſtriſſimi, the Princes fortiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi, with al theire nobilitey: vnder who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earthe tremblethe, &amp; the worlde qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe. On the other ſyde are the graue Preſedentes, the prudent Counſaylors, the facounde Aduocates, and eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyers,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:3"/>
with theyre cruell bandes: amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt whom, ſome do ſet vp the galowes, ſome other do prepare the fagotes, other ſome haue in theyre handes, Gyvers, Fet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, Manacles, and all other kynde of tortures redy to put them in practyſſe.</p>
            <p>On the other ſyde, are the worſhupfull maſter Doctore, the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Bachelors, the venerable Rectors, the lerned Regen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, the wyſſe Maſters, and all ſhuche o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, redy fornyſhed with theyre wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. What ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preuaylle agaynſt ſo myghty an arme? Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſſe that take part with Ieſus Chriſt, which ſeme to be ſo feable? Seynge that the moſt part off them are people poore off ſpirete, ſimple as doves, ſhepe affociſion, with out ryches, voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de off fryndes, extemed apoſtates, dyſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced craftesmen, handy laborers, vnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, expoſed to all dangers, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned as vnprofytable, expelled, whypped, banyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hed ſcaffolded, weryed, travayled, nyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, deiected, impriſoned, ſtocked, fette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and deſtituted off all defence, excepte off that tow edged ſworde, which ys the worde off God: Agaynſt whom, in the meane tyme, the aduerſaryes do conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, conſulte conſpire, coniure: do wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them ſelfes, battell them ſelfes, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyfye
<pb facs="tcp:185137:4"/>
them ſelfes, do imagen, enterpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte, do ſowe abrod lyinge letters, ſklanderous reportes, vntrew tales, ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>genynge vayne thynges, they thounder, they tempeſte, they roar, and attempt al poſſible meanes, to ruinate and dyſtroye them: They on the other ſyde, wepynge, faſtynge, praynge blyſhynge, diſſemblyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge theyre ſorrowe, coverynge theyre hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vynes, ſacreficynge vnto God theyre tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, abydynge in this worlde no thynge but blowes, ſtrypes, contumeles, torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, paynes, greffes, moleſtations and mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeryes. Yff then ſhuche be not conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted by the holy ſcryptures, wherin only ys all refuge, Ioye &amp; delecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: how can they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinewe without loſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of corrage? What man off warre ys the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re be he nev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> ſo valiante, whoſſe enymes ſemynge inuiſible, and ſeynge hym ſelfe ſodenly incloſed with them, that ys not forth with abaſhed &amp; diſmayed, vnleſſe he be boldened with a ſure perſwaſion of notable &amp; honorable victorye? And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rywyſſe what ys he ſo feable and faynte herted that ſeynge before his eyes his vic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torious captayne ſkyrmyſhynge with his enymes, brekynge theyre araye, beatynge downe the mightieſt, ouertrowynge the
<pb facs="tcp:185137:4"/>
valienteſte and, and levynge the reſte effe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minated, diſcorraged, weryed, and all moſte dyſcomfited, that wyll not pull vp his ſtomake and boldly thruſte hym ſelfe into the battayll, and ſpecially hauynge a ſure promys off his Capitayne to be crowned with triumphe after the fygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. And doth not this frute off perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce proſede from the pleaſant tre off conſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation? who all wayes promyſeth, a ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full iſſewe after ſorrowe, calmnes after tempeſte, lyght after darknes, ſwetnes af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſowrnes, perpetuall peace after a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment off vnquietnes, infinite glorye after a lytell payne? The father off all mercye and God off all conſolation,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte the vs in all oure tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we may be able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte them that are in any manner off trouble, with the ſame comforte where with we oure ſelues are conforted off hym: and as the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons off Chriſte are plentious in vs, and in al that are his, that even ſo every one off vs may be plentious in conſolation by Chriſte. For this cauſe then, as the moſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te leſte warryoure, I haue wyllyngly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodated my ſelfe, to incorrage to the vttermoſt off my power my followe ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioures that now do ſuſtayne the wayght
<pb facs="tcp:185137:5"/>
and bronte off the batayll. And as in a battayll all are nat appoynted to fyght &amp; ſtrycke, but ſome to ſounde the trompet, ſome the drome and ſome to playe vpon the phiffe, therby to encorrage the ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oures: even ſo I can do no les, &amp; all other that there vnto are called with me, but to noyſe the phiffe, to vſe the pen, to plaie with my fyngers vpon the Davideicall harpe, to ſounde the prophetical trompet and to ſtryke vp the Euangelicall drome, therby to anymate and corrag to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayll the hertes off the worthy warryors and valiante ſoldiours off Ieſus Chriſte: exteminge on my parte to haue muche pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyted, yff with the ſounde off this lytell phiffe, I may any thynge confort the fain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te herted, anymate the weake corraged, &amp; ſtrenghten thoſſe that by feablenes do ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halte with the tyme, or ſtraye a ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, to thende they may be reſtored vnto theyre former vigoure and boldnes agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: for even for them chefly do I preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſounde it: truſtynge to reſſayve double Ioye there by, yff in any thynge it may profyte them: Knowyng the moſt valiant and ſtrongeſt ſoldiours, at the ſondrye noyſes off trompetes and dromes ſounded vplo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ago to haue all redy wonderfully
<pb facs="tcp:185137:5"/>
put theyre enymes to the foyle: off who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">As off, Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ridlye, Hopꝑ, Bradforthe, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Pot, Tayler, Farrer, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dmaker, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, vvith many other vvorthy vvarriours.</note> ſome hauynge trauarſed the batail, by fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, by watter, by ſworde &amp; divers other tormentes which they haue ſuffred in paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyng thorowe: haue now preuaylled ouer theyre enymes, &amp; do were the triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phant crowne off glorye. The other as yet beyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge in the greateſt thronge off the batayll, do moſt valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly and corragiouſly ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne the violent aſſautes of thoſſe Elephan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Lyons, Beares, Tigers, Bores, Wolfes, Dogges, Bulles, and all other ſhuch cruell kynde off beaſtes, in whoſſe aſſautes they are ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly anymated to penetrate the breache of theyre aduerſary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. To thende then that I do not rone at an vncertayne thynge,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> nor fyght as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne that beatethe the ayre? I haue put my felfe into the arraye with the fayghtfull Champions off Ieſus Chriſte, for to ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the alarom agaynſt his enymyes: And all though this my phiffe do make no gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at noyſe, for that it ys but lytell: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the les he that wyll gyve atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyve ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vnto the ſame (in myn opinion) ſhall fynde the ſame replete with ſufficient har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monye, and not yll agreynge with the tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petes, clarious and dromes that hath byn ſounded all redy, all thought his tune be
<pb facs="tcp:185137:6"/>
not ſo hyghe. I am ryght well aſſured that it ſhall playe no thynge out off the tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne off Godes worde, which thynge cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſethe me to iudge that it ſhalbe the better harde. Beſydes that, the tow perſons ſet forthe in this dialogue are ryght worthy that we ſhoulde gyve them audience: For the one ys the Churche or Congregation off Chriſte, and the other ys the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor or the comfortor. I ſaye notablye the Churche off Chriſte, the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation off the fayghtfull where ſo ever they be, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte to God eternal lyffe: and not the Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deicall Synagoge, nor the Mahometical broude, nor all the papiſticall Rable, nor yet none off the hereticall Sectaryes: all the which haue no parte in this churche, founded vpon the doctryne off the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and Prophetes: The which Churche ys introduced in this dialogue, as ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, mornynge, troubled, and diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by cauſe off the oppreſſions, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, calamites, afflictions and tormen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes wherewith the wycked vngodly tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and perſecutors do moleſte hyr: &amp; that only by cauſe that ſhe ſuſtaynethe, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dethe, mayntaynethe &amp; ſupportethe the quarrell off hyr God: off whom ſhe feare the to be forſaken, abandoned and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:6"/>
as ſome tyme it ſemethe that ſhe ys, by cauſe of hyr ſynnes. And therfor moſt aptly ys there alſo introduced a Conſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor for the other Collocutor, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to his name dothe conſolate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, and fortifye hyr: allegynge vnto hyr manye worthy ſentences &amp; notable places off the holy ſcriptures, which do aſſure hyr off the aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; healpe off hyr God, off his good wyll, and diuine prouidence towardes hyr: promyſynge a moſt ſhort &amp; perfyte delyurance off hyr Croſſe, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyne off hyr enymee, and a croune off in credible glorye: wher with finally ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentethe hyr felfe, and dependethe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame with great confidence. I doute not that any wyll ſaye, they are tow perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ill appropriated: for in myn opinion it ys not poſſible to accomodate and copell to gyther for this preſent tyme, tow per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons more apte and proper. What thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ys there in the worlde more afflicted, then the Churche off Chriſte? And what thynge ys more worthy all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe? Truly there ys not one off all thoſſe that notte them ſelfes to be hyr fryndes, that dothe comforte hyr: But rather thoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that wonte to boſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to be hyr cheffe fryndes and familiers haue vtterly
<pb facs="tcp:185137:7"/>
contemned and diſpyced hyr. where are the goodly conſolations that, that gentyll galla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the Pope (who boſtethe hym ſelfe to be hyr hedde) with all his Clargye, (who preache the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves to be hyr pillers) that they do miniſter vnto hyr? Are not theſſe theye that ffyrſt off all crye out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte hyr, and vpon hyr, to the fyre, to the fyre? What ſupporte fyndethe ſhe off the kynges and prices of this worlde, that ſo muche afflicte hyr on euery ſyde (exſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te off a very fewe) who not withſtandin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ought to be hyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſes? But how ſhoulde they comforte this ſo poore afflic Churche, which they eſteme as the of cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge off the worlde, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as by moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell warres and blouddy battailles they do ſo miſerablye devoure theyre owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſubiectes? We muſte then ſearche ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me other Conſolator and comfortor, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſſe before named. But in ſearchynge we ſhall not fynde the trew Conſolator a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where els, but where as ſhe ys, to wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te,<note place="margin">prou. 30.</note> in God only, who all wayes dothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolate the humble and afflicted, in gyvyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge them eternall conſolation by his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, the which ys aſure defence &amp; buckler, vnto all thoſſe that truſte in the ſame: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt reſſayve hyr. For which
<pb facs="tcp:185137:7"/>
cauſe I haue holpen my ſelfe with the .129 pſalme off Dauid, which ſemethe vnto me very fytt for the purpoſe. For in the ſame, the ſtate off the Churche, of hyr per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutions and afflictions, and off hyr per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſecutors, with the Iſſew and ende as well off hyr that ys perſecuted, as off hyr perſecutors, ys ſo fully dyſtrybed. that with mythe a do there can be founde any one place more fytt for this purpoſe, all though that through out all the Pſaul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter this ſonge be often repeted. And I woulde to God that all thoſſe that ſynge the pſalmes takynge pleaſure in the voyce may in ſhuche ſorte taſte the wordes and ſence off the ſame, that they may reſſayve as muche conſolation in theyre ſoules by the depe conſyderation theroff as they gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve melodye to theyr eares by theyr voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, the which with out the ſence ys all to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther vnprofytable. I wyll confeſſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that I haue more ſerched in this Pſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, that which ſeruethe to the purpoſe off the dialogue, to comforte the fayght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and weake, then any exquyſyte or ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll interpretation, that may be gathered and borowed out off the bokes off ſhuche as haue wrytten vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pſaulter. But me thynkes that I here al redy ſome that
<pb facs="tcp:185137:8"/>
ſaye with Nathanaell? Can there come a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny good thynge out off Nazarethe? To whom I wyll anſwere: Come and ſe. A lytel veſſell ſomtyme contaynethe good ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quoure. And it ys not ſo myche to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed on, what the veſſell ys, nor whens it comethe, ſo the lyquoure be good that ys drawen out off it. Fynally, this lytell, beynge reſſayved and accepted in good par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and that it dothe engender ſome good appetyte in the harte off thoſſe that with ſaffe to taſte the ſame: It ſhal occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to take pleaſure to prepare ſome other diſhe no leſſe delectable to the taſte then this ys: But the vometyng vp off this, wyll cauſe me to ceaſe from the reſte, for it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re but loſt laboure and exſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces yll imploi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to prepare meate, and no man to haue any appetyte to eate it. And yet this my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wyl I ſaye, that he ys very yll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oned, and hathe vtterly loſt his ſtomake and taſte, that cannot digeſte &amp; ſavor this lytell morſell off meate, ſeynge that it ys all to gyther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſed &amp; prepared off hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fections, in the which chefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ethe the lyffe off man, who lyvethe not by brede only, but by every worde that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedethe out off the mouthe off God, off the which it ys ſayed that it ys lyke the rai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:185137:8"/>
&amp; ſnowe which cometh downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and retornethe not thyther agayne,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.</note> but watereth the eat the and makethe it frutfull &amp; grene, that it may gyve corne vnto the ſower, and brede vnto hym that eateth: Even ſo the worde of God dothe not retorne to hym in vayne, but dothe ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhe his wyll, &amp; proſper in the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges where vnto he ſendethe it. Thoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are to muche ſimple, that followynge the hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grey fooles, do imploye theyre mony in that which ys no brede, &amp; theyre labour about the thynge that dothe not ſatiſfye and wyll not gyve eare vnto the lorde to eate the thynge that ys good,<note place="margin">Sapi. 7.</note> to thende theyre ſoul may haue pleaſure in his plen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiouſnes. The lorde gyve vs his wyſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, in the which ys the ſpiret off vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge, which ys holy, intere, plenty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, ſubtyll, courtoys, diſcrete, quycke, vndefyled, playne, ſwete, lovynge the thynge that ys good, ſharpe, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byddeth not to do well, gentyll, kynde, ſtedfaſte, ſure, fre, hauynge all vertues, ſyrcomſpecte in all thynges, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendethe all ſpiretes off vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge, beyng pure &amp; ſharpe. </p>
            <closer>So be it.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:185137:9"/>
            <head>¶ A moſte comfortable dialo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue betwyne the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor / and the Churche.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen as I do behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and conſyder the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, the Spouce off Ieſus Chriſte, the Electe and cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen off God, by the malice off men, to be ſo evell han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled, and vnworthelye entreated: ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge vnder the croſſe, fatigated with ſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes, buffited with blowes, ſeaſoned with ſorrowe, travelynge in travaile as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man redy to be delyvered: beynge moued with compaſſion, I deſyre erneſtly to co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monicate with hyr, and to comforte hyr to the vtter moſte off my power: to then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de I may ſome what aſſwage hyr ſorrowe and induce hyr to a vertious and conſtant perſeuerance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 3.</note>How lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge O God infinitly good, wilt thow abandon and leave me to the crual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye off intractable tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes?<note place="margin">Gene. 3.</note> It ſemethe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perly, O my lorde, that thow haſt ſet me
<pb facs="tcp:185137:9"/>
as a butt agaynſt thyne arrowe:<note place="margin">Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 3</note> For I do moſt bitterly feale the ſharpe ſtynge of the ſerpent agaynſte my hele: Not witſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng thow knoweſt ryght well the wron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that ys done vnto me, and how myne enymes do ſharpy purſewe me, and hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me out as a byrde: Yea &amp; that with out a cauſe. And yet all this whyll O eternal God thow doeſte diſſimule and holde thy peace, and ſemeſte that thow haſte forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>Ioye be with the, grace, peace, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye from God the father &amp; from the Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de Ieſus Chriſte, O thow beſt beloved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt all other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>What ioye ys that thow greteſt me with all, that am aſſauted with ſo many enymes?<note place="margin">Tobi. 5. Iudg. 5. pſal. 65.</note> And yff I be ſo myche beloved as thow ſayeſte, wher for then are all the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſe thynges happyned vnto me? Where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all the marvayles off the lorde that are expreſſed vnto me in his holy ſcriptures? He hath with drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his hande,<note place="margin">pſal. 89.</note> his ryght arme ys hyd in his beſome. His wrath<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full diſpleaſures are gone ouer me, &amp; his ferefulnes hathe oppreſſed me: They do dayly compaſſe me about lyke water, and
<pb facs="tcp:185137:10"/>
they haue incloſed me on euery ſyde. My Lovers and fryndes hathe he put awaye from me, and ſhuche as are off myn ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quayntance,<note place="margin">pſal. 90.</note> are in darknes and hyd out off my ſyghte. Where are now his fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte mercyes become, that he ſware to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vnto me before, by his fayghte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>In herynge the mone and complayne thow ſhalt poſſible cauſe thoſſe that haue not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, to be abaſhed &amp; aſtoyned. I do not as yet perſayve the cauſe off thy lamentation: onles it be, by cauſe thow wareſt aged, which naturally lovethe reſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te: parauenture it greuethe the to endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re payne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>I do not denye but that I am olde, &amp; off a great Age, yea lovynge reſte: But I am not as yet ſo feble, neyther hathe ſtrenght ſo vtterly forſaken me, but that (by the grace off my God) I purpoſe fyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely to reſyſte thoſſe ſtryffes and battayl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les that are erected agaynſt me. And wheras thow calleſte me aged, It ought not to abaſhe the for that I mone my ſelfe: for as muche as it ys comonly ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, euery aged co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnethe his ſorrowe. And forther more, it ys no dyſhonour vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:185137:10"/>
me to complayne and caſt forthe my ſob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bynge ſyghtes before my ſpouce, therby to prouoke hym to inclyne to helpe me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>Agaynſte whome?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>Doeſt thow make inquiſition of a thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſo apparant? doeſt thow not ſe how I am dayly compaſſed about with moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell beſtes, as Lyons, Beares, Tigres, Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>opardes, Wolves, Foxes,<note place="margin">pſal. 79.</note> that ſeke no thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge els but to devoure me? They haue gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for meate vnto the byrdes off the aye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, the dead bodyes of my chyldrin: And the fleſhe off my holy ones vnto the beſtes off the lande: Theye ſhede theyre bloude lyke water: They are become an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me vnto theyre enymes, and a very ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; deryſion vnto them that are rounde about them: And yet thow aſkeſte, agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte whome? Beholde Fraunce, Italye, Spayne, Flanders, and now alſo Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and all other ſhuche contryes, &amp; thow ſhalt ſee theyre priſons full off my chylde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rin, the aſhes off ſome fleynge in the aye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, the bloude off others trodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder fot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, ſome tremblynge in theyre howſes a bydynge an vniuſte iuſtice, other ſome al ſorowfull fleynge awaye, leue wyffe and
<pb facs="tcp:185137:11"/>
childrin: ſome levynge theyre goodes, are as ſlaves in ſtrange landes: other ſome in teares and ſorrowe do ende theyre dayes in the hyghe wayes, voyde off all honeſt buryall: And yet thow aſkeſte what I ay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le? Ys not this a ſufficient cauſe for me to morne and complayne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>It is ſo. But what more haue they do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Texte.</note>They haue vexed me, they haue made a thowſande aſſautes agaynſte me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>This ys not only then happyned off la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te vnto the: How longe ys it ſyns?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Texte.</note>Even from my byrthe hytherto, even from the tender age off my youthe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>Thow art then very ſtronge, ſeynge thow haſte byn able ſo longe tyme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte the grevous aſſautes off ſo many eny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">pſal. 18.</note>They had long a gone ſpoyled and dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troyed me, yff the lorde God (who is my ſtony rocke and my defence) had not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued me. But in his protection I do re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayne
<pb facs="tcp:185137:11"/>
invincible:<note place="margin">Texte.</note> ſo that hyther to myn enymes haue not vanqueſhed me, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vayled agaynſt me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>Dyd they but only moleſte and torment the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>The Plowers plowed vpon my backe,<note place="margin">Texte.</note> and made longe forrowes: yea they dyd purpoſe to haue bounde me with theyre cordes, and vtterly to haue vndone me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>And what happyned? who hyndered them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>But the Lorde that ys ryghtous hathe hewen the ſnares of the vngodly in peces.<note place="margin">Texte.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, be off good chere, ſeynge thow art vnder the ſhadow and ſafgarde off ſhuche a lorde: for all thoſe that hate the ſhalbe confounded and torned backe. They ſhalbe even as the graſſe growynge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the howſſe toppes, which wythereth a fore it be plucked vp:<note place="margin">Texte.</note> Wheroff the mower fyllethe not his hande, nor the gle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner his boſome: ſo that they which go by, ſay not ſo muche as the lorde proſper you: we wyſhe you good lucke in the name off the Lorde</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:185137:12"/>Truly thow haſte comforted me, and haſte ſpoken to the contentation of my her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eſai. 61.</note>Even therfor am I come, to comforte the. For the lorde hath ſent me to brynge glade tydynges vnto the afflicted, to byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vp the wounded hertes, to preache de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyverance to the captyve, and to open the priſon to them that are bounde, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te them that are in heavynes, &amp; that bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye myght be gyven vnto them in the ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de off aſhes, the oyle off ioye in the ſtede of lamentation, and pleaſant rayment for a hevy mynde. It is no reaſon then that to the, beynge ſo deſyrous off the glorye off God, I ſhoulde denye that which only thow art worthy off. And ſo myche the rather do I it wyllyngly and gladly, for that I knowe, it ſhall torne to thy como<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite. Wherfor then, as thowchynge the fyrſte parte (O vertious Churche) wheras thow complayneſte that they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vexed and tormented the wroughtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye? Art thow ignorant off this, that to haue the grayne off corne out off the ere, it muſt be fyrſt threſſhed, and then fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned before it can be ſeperated from the chaffe? To make wyne, behovethe it not fyrſt of all to gather the grape, and after to bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:185137:12"/>
it to the preſſe, to thende the good wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne may be ſeperated from the huſkes?</p>
               <p>Doth it greve the then, that God purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge to place the in his grayner, dothe ſeperate the from the chaffe (prepared for the fyre inextinguible) by a lytel threſhin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge &amp; betynge? Art thow ſory, that beinge put into the new barrelles of the lorde, thow art not caſt forthe with the huſkes vnto the hogges?<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> I thynke well that this affliction which thow now ſuffereſt, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the not ſeme vnto the to be Ioyous, but grevous: but be aſſured that afterwarde it bryngethe the quyete frute off ryghtouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are excerciſed thereby. For truly the lorde wylbe the defence of al thyne, early in the mornynge,<note place="margin">Eſai. 33. 2. Cor. 4.</note> and theyr healthe in the tyme of trouble: the which ys but momentany and lyghte, and yet it preparethe an exceadynge and an eternal wayghte off glorye for the fayghtfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> whoſſe afflictions in this lyffe as I ſuppoſe are not worthy off the glory to come,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.</note> which then ſhalbe ſhowed vpon them. Doſte not thow remember that Moyſes beynge greate, and elevated into honour, refuſed to be called the ſonne off Pharaos daughter. Chuſynge rather to ſuffer aduerſite with the people of God,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:13"/>
then to enioye the pleaſures off ſynne for a ceaſon, extemynge the rebuke off Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te greater ryches then the treaſures of E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gypte, hauynge reſpecte vnto the rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de?<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.</note> Dyd not thy ſonne Paul ſaye, that he was excedynge ioyous in all his tribu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lations?<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> And other thyne apoſtles dyd they not in departynge from the counſayll re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyſe that they were counted worthy to ſuffer rebuke for the name of Ieſus Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te?<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> Is it not alſo gyven to the fayghtful for Chriſte, not only to beleve in hym, but alſo to ſuffer for his name ſake, hauin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge a lyke fyghte?<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> For it ys a trew ſaynge, that thoſſe that are dead with Chriſte, ſhal alſo lyve with hym, &amp; thoſſe that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer with hym ſhall alſo raigne with him. Dauid ſo often tymes oppreſſed with tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bulation, dothe he not contynewally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte hym ſelfe in the confidence off the promyſes off God, as it apperethe in the 10.17.22, 25. pſalmes, as in divers other? Even ſo then knowynge that all thynges proſperous or aduerſe do worke for the beſt vnto them that loue god:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Ceaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy lamentations and comfort thy ſelfe in hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>Off good rygh I ought to love the, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:185137:13"/>
reuerence the, (O Conſolator) in repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge my ſelfe happy to haue mett with the, no thynge doutynge but that thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge vnto me ys a ſynguler gyfte off God. Wherfor perſwadynge my ſelfe off thyne accuſtomed cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye, I wyll de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vyce ſo myche the more familiarly with the: Let it not ſeme ſtrange vnto the the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that I do move vnto the the ſame queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the holy prophet Ieremie ſo myche experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with afflictions:<note place="margin">Iere 12. Pſal 73. Iob. 21. Abac. 1.</note> Dauid ſo faightful &amp; renowmed a kynge: Iob the iuſte, the invincyble rocke of pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: &amp; Abacuc the vertious, haue done: al they not a lytell meruelynge to ſe the wycked abounde in proſperite. And for my parte I am not ſo myche perplexed and ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for all the oultrages and iniures that they do vnto me in my me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, as to ſe the holy name off my God blaſphemed, blamed, &amp; defamed. As alſo to heare that the Seducers, are called holy Doctors. People co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious, good Religious. The Apoſtates, Apoſtles. The wycked, v<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The perſecutors, zelators. The polu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, vndefiled: And contrarywyſſe the peace makers are ſayd to be heretykes, &amp; troublers off comen wealthes: and good people are extemed worſſe then dogges:
<pb facs="tcp:185137:14"/>
But yet the thynge that moſt troubleth my chyldren: and miniſtreth matter off pryde vnto the ignorant, ys, that the lorde ſemethe interely to reſiſte agaynſt thoſſe that by al meanes ſeke to avaunce his glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye: and on the other ſyde ys fauorable vnto thoſſe that do reſiſte hym with all theyre power: from the which thynge on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly proceadeth that divers do affirme, the evell to be good, and the good to be evell: lyght to be darknes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.</note> and darknes to be lyght: ſower to be ſwete, and ſwete to be ſower. I coulde produce vnto the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent examples hereof out off all ages paſt, yff we had not now in theſſe dayes ſome preſently preſte before oure eyes. What fayghtfull man ys there, that dothe not ſobb and mourne when as he remembre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the that miſerable realme eff England? Whoſſe eyes are ſo dryed vp, that dothe not diſtyll plenty off teares, to be holde, A lande ſo floryſhynge, A kynge ſo wel in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtructed, Churches ſo well reformed, to haue had ſo ſodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a fall, ſo ſpedy a rewy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and ſo haſty an ouerthrowe? Was there euer tragedy more tyrryble, horror more horrible, and iudgment more adme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable? To beholde the holy ſeruyce off God and his diuine worde ſo tyrannouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:185137:14"/>
trodden vnder fotte, dyſdaynfully diſſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piced, and contemptiouſly corrupted: and contrarywyſſe the ſervyle ſuperſticious ſervyces off idoles erected and avanſed. What may the wycked ſeduced ſaye at this preſent, or at leſt wayes (all though they ſpeke not) what do they thynke? Do they not ſaye, that eyther the worde that was preched off late, was not the pure worde off God, or els they thynke that God ys weaker then the devell, ſeynge that he dothe not defende and mayntay-his worde. Ys not this an intollerable blaſphemye and worthy to be lamented?</p>
               <p>where fore yff there be any exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſte,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> yff there by any conſolation off charite, I praye the power forthe theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>I wyll not depreue the off that, for the which (as I ſayed before) I was ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the. Wherefor to ſatiſfye vnto thy firſte requeſte, wherby thow we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teft about to prove the occaſion of thy ſorrowe to be iuſte, allegynge for the ſame divers teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes worthy off credyte which here to fore were produced off ſhuche as were perplexed as thow art now: The one purpoſynge to diſpute with God, and to
<pb facs="tcp:185137:15"/>
talke in iudgment with hym.<note place="margin">Iere. 12. Pſal. 73. Iob. 21. Abac. 1.</note> The other ſayinge that his fette were al moſt gon, &amp; his treadynges had well nye ſlypte. The thyrde troublynge hym ſelfe ſayed that fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re had poceſſed his fleſhe. And the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the complaynethe to haue cryed viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, &amp; yet not hearde. Wherin it behoueth the to vnderſtande that not witſtandynge the fidelite, vertu, and piete of theſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly men, yet had they theyr humayne af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, off the which the ſcriptures hath not kepte ſylence, to declare therby that no thynge ys perfytt but one only God, who hath eaſely pardoned them that fau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, wherin alſo they dyd not remayne, as wery well declareth theyre godly ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges afterwardes. Forther more it may be ſayed with out ſtraynge from the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the that ſhuche queſtions are as exceſſyve admirations off myndes, tranſported and rapte into the iudgment off God. Conſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derynge that a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after,<note place="margin">Abac. 1.</note> one off the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: O lorde my God my holy one, thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne eyes are clere, thow mayſt not ſe evel, thow canneſt not beholde the thynge that ys wycked. The other dothe he not ſaye with a great confidence:<note place="margin">Iere. 12.</note> But thow Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to whom I am well knowen, thow haſt ſene me, and proved my herte? And
<pb facs="tcp:185137:15"/>
Dauid comynge to hym ſelfe dothe he not ſaye by and by after:<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> Yea I had all moſt ſayed eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they, but Lo then I ſhould haue comdemned the generation off the chyldren off God, vntyll I went into the ſanctuarye off the lorde, then vnderſtode I the ende off the wycked?<note place="margin">Iob. 21.</note> But Iob ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge more profoundly ſayed: who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che God any knowlege, in as myche as he hathe the hygheſt power off all? For other wyſſe it ys wrytten:<note place="margin">Eſa. 45.</note> Curſed be he that ſtryuethe againſte his maker, as the pott agaynſt the potter: ſeynge that he ys that great lorde formynge the lyghte, and creatynge darknes, makynge peace, and creatynge aduerſite: Hathe he not created the waſter to diſtroye?<note place="margin">Iob. 5.</note> Ys not he alſo the almyghty, that makethe the wounde, &amp; layethe to the playſter? that hurtethe and makethe whole agayne?<note place="margin">Iob. 9.</note> Who ſhall ſaye vnto hym the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherfore doſte thow this or that, and be reputed innocent? And therefore the iuſtice off his wyll ys a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient contentation in this behalfe: not witſtandynge the ſcriptures dothe here &amp; there declare certayne cauſes. Wherfor then as to wchynge the wycked, I beleue that thow art not offended with the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that God dothe vnto them.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> Cauſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:185137:16"/>
his ſonne to ſhyne vpon them, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge them rayne,<note place="margin">Math. 20</note> as to the good: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyſſe that great father off how ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de myght iuſtly allege agaynſt the, that which was ſayed vnto the murmerynge laborers: Ys it not lawfull for me to do with myne owne what I wyl? And, thyn eye, ys it evel by cauſe I am good: But I perſayve very well that the cheffe cauſe why thow art offended, ys, to beholde the godly comtemned, diſpyced, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, oppreſſed, and God in them dyſhono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red: Thow haſte all redy harde how that every man in this reſpecte ought to capty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vate his vnderſtandynge, and to ſubdew hym ſelfe vnto the pleaſure off God, as he hath alſo wylled vs to praye, That his wyll be done in earth as it ys in heaven, beynge ryche and plentyfull in bothe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note>For all the wholl heavens are the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the earthe hath he gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren off men: yea even to the wycked to thende that there by they myght be made inexcuſable,<note place="margin">Iob. 9.</note> when as God ſhall reproche them off theyr ingratitude, and that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was no lett in hym why they ſhould not be reſſayved into the ryches off the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall kyngdom: ſeynge that he hath all redy ſo benyngly allured them there vnto
<pb facs="tcp:185137:16"/>
by earthly goodes and pleaſures. Even ſo was it anſwered vnto that wycked Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues beynge in tormentes in hell:<note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> Sonne (ſayed Abraham vnto hym in whoſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome was Lazarus one off thy chyldren) remember that thow reſſayvedſt felicyte in this lyffe, and Lazarus reſſayved pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and now ys he comforted, and thow art tormented. Even ſo then the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked neyther belevynge nor ſcerchynge any thynge els but thynges temporall: God dothe gyve vnto them ſome tyme, for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſpeciall reſpecte, proſperyte: wherin alſo ſhynethe forthe the greatnes off his mercye. And this truly may ſuffice to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente the: vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge that god reſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge to thoſſe that are his, the celeſtial treaſour and ryches to come, he wyll not haue them to mvſe &amp; to be carfull about the felicites and pleaſures off this worlde: which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to the thynges eternall are no thynge but vanite and miſerye.</p>
               <p>And all be it that he hathe ſome tyme gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſome off his fayghtfull ſervantes abondance off ryches, as to Abraham, I<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaac, Dauid, and others: yet hathe he al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes myxed theſame with many aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites &amp; troubles, be cauſe he woulde with drawe theyr hertes from thynges cadu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb facs="tcp:185137:17"/>
and corruptible, to ſtablyſhe theſame on thynges perfytt and durable. But myche more ſyns the comynge off Chriſte, who knowynge fully the wyll off his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath more amplye expreſſed as well by doctryne, as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation that by many tribulations it behoueth vs to enter into the kyngdom off heaven.<note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> And he hym ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe beynge ſett forthe for a ſygne off contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diction,<note place="margin">Luc. 2. Hebr. 12.</note> for the ioye that was ſett before him, abode the croſſe, diſpiced the ſhame, and ſuffred ſhuche gayne ſayinge off ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners agaynſte hym. It ought not then to greve them that beare his name, to be are alſo his marke: neyther ought the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers to preſume to pas by any other waie then the hedd hath done. For the father hath ſet hym forthe for an example vnto all that are his, and we muſt aſke non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon theroff, but that which the apoſtell. S. Paul gyvethe, to wytt, that God hath made the wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off this worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de folyſhnes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> in that it pleaſethe hym by the preachynge off the croſſe (which the worlde reputeth foliſhnes) to ſave thoſſe that beleue:<note place="margin">1. pet. 4.</note> who ought not to be abaſhed when as they are proved, as in a fornace, in as myche as they do comonycate in the afflictions off Chriſte. who not witſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge
<pb facs="tcp:185137:17"/>
hath ſuffred for an other occaſion and purpoſe, then do his fayghtfull, as alſo his bloude ys off an other nature the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ys the bloude of his marters:<note place="margin">1. pet. 3.</note> For Chriſte hath ſuffred for the ſynnes of all the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, the ryghtouſe for the vnryghtouſe, as he in whoſſe mouthe there was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de no gyle: But thow moſt comonly in the perſon of thy children,<note place="margin">pſal. 32.</note> thow ſuffreſte for thy ſynnes, the which nev<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> the les it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſethe the lorde to hyde and couer, and through hys inexplicable mercye not to impute them vnto the: But rather in thyne afflictions makethe the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto the image of his ſonne,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. Hebr. 5</note> who hath lerned obedience by the thynges that he hath ſuffred: whoſe bloud alſo dothe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce and budd forthe better thynges, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bloud off thoſſe that are thyne: For the bloud of Chriſte dothe bowe and incly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne God to mercye,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> and publyſhethe the glade tidynges of peace. Wher as the blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de off thy chyldren prouokethe the iuſtyce of God,<note place="margin">Gene. 4. Apoc. 6.</note> and cryethe for vengance agayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte thoſſe that ſhede theſame, to whom co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundment ys gyven to reſte a lytell, tyll ſhuch tyme as the nomber off theyre followe ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhed: &amp; theyre brytherne who muſt be ſlayne, as they
<pb facs="tcp:185137:18"/>
are. Whereby it apperethe that the nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber off the ſanctifyed marters off Chriſte are not yet accomplyſhed.<note place="margin">3. Reg. 19</note> Forther more when as Helias dyd complayne to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fte alone, hauynge the zeale off the lorde: Anſwer was made vnto hym that in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el there were yet reſerved .vij. m. whoſſe knes were neuer bowed before Baall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note>This ys a nother cauſe alſo off the paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of God, that for the love off his chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren dothe ſome tyme ſpare the wycked, whom he by his longe contynewed pacien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and benyngnyte dothe inuitate and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke to repentance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>Thow haſte greatly recreated and forty fyed my ſpirete, with thy ſwete ſayinges: ſo that thow haſt al moſt dryed vp my tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res: or at leaſt wyſſe changed them: for whereas before I dyd bewayle with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe off herte the afflictions off my chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, thow doeſt now mynyſter matter vnto me to ſorrow rather the impiete off myne adv<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ſaryes, in hearynge the ſaye, that the terryble recompenſe off theyre wyckednes ys eternal deathe: &amp; that the paynes off my chyldren ys but momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, abydynge an infinite glorye. But I pray the expreſſe vnto me more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly
<pb facs="tcp:185137:18"/>
by the teſtimonyes off the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures this matter, accordynge vnto the good gyfte that god hath gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the,<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in only reſtethe all my ioye and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: for thow doeſt allege no texte vnto me that doth not perſe even to the devy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge a ſonder off the ſoull and the ſpire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and off the ioyntes and mare.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for I requyre the off the ſame remunerati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, as off my chylde, and as I haue ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my herte vnto the, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo inlarge me thyne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhalbe to me no ſmall pleaſure to in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce the to yelde thy ſelfe laudable in all thynges, as the ſeruante off God,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> in my the tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in afflictions, in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in angueſhes, in ſtrypes, in impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonmentes, in ſtryves, in labours, in pacience, by the armour off ryghtouſnes off the ryght hande, and on the lefte han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, by honour and dyſhonour, by evel re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porte &amp; good reporte, in ſhuche ſorte that thy chyldren beynge extemed as dyſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and yet founde verytable, as deiyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and yet lyvynge, as chaſtyned and yet not kylled, as ſorrowynge and yet alway<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es merye, as poore and yet makynge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ryche, as hauynge no thynge and yet
<pb facs="tcp:185137:19"/>
poceſſynge all thynges.<note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> Yea it ys alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they do accomplyſhe that which ys lefte behynde off the paſſions of Chriſte in theyre fleſhe as longe as they are in this worlde: berynge allwayes eve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry where in theyre bodyes the mortifyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion off the lorde Ieſus,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4</note> that the lyffe off Ieſus Chriſte myght appere in theyre bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes,<note place="margin">1. pet. 4.</note> with out beynge aſhamed, yff they be afflicted as chriſteans: knowynge that they do gloryfye God in that behalfe: for at the apparynge off the glorye of Chriſte they ſhall reioyce with an inexplicable gladnes. The which thynge alſo Ieſus Chriſte dothe very aptly declare by a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per ſimylytude,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> A woman (ſayeth he) when ſhe travaylethe, hath ſorrowe, by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe hyr houre ys come, but as ſone as ſhe ys delyvered off the chylde, ſhe reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brethe no more the anguyſhe, for the ioye that a man ys borne into the worlde, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo he promyſethe that after theyre ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe he wyll ſe them agayne and theyre hertes ſhall reioyce, the which ioye no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall take from them, ſayinge forther more vnto them, In the worlde ye ſhall haue tribulation, but in me ye ſhall haue peace, &amp; in the ende he dothe e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corrage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this ſayinge, that he hath ov<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>come
<pb facs="tcp:185137:19"/>
the worlde. To this purpoſe alſo ſerue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th very well the parabole that ys propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto Eſdras,<note place="margin">4. Eſd. 7.4.</note> of a ſumptious Cyte ſet in a dangerous place, the entrance very narrowe &amp; yll to come to, for at the ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d there ys fyre, &amp; a depe water at the lef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and but one lytell ſtrayte pathe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyrte them bothe, to wytt, betwyxte the water and the fyre, ſo ſmall that the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynethe but the bredth off one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Yff this Cyte were now gyven to an hey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, and he never went through the pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous waye how woulde he enioye his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herytance? Even ſhuche ys the portion off thy chyldren. The which ſimilitude Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte confirmethe ſaiynge,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> that the waye ys narrowe that leadethe vnto lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, and fewe there be that enter there by. There ys no doute but that this narrowe waye, ys the pathe of afflyction:<note place="margin">1. pet, 4.</note> as it ys ſayed that the iuſte ys ſcarſely ſaved by ſuffrynge: And the cauſe ys, that Adam hauynge ons tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſed the conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s off the lorde,<note place="margin">4. Eſd. 10</note> the entrance off the lyffe to come was forth with made ſtrayte, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and paynfull. And all be it that the ſame be comone as well to the fayghtfull as to the vnbelevers: yet ys it ſo, that the almyghty God wyllynge to declare his po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer towardes his chyldren doethe cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:185137:20"/>
them to come to theyre determyned and moſt happy ende, by thynges that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye: to wytte, to ſoveraigne felycite by great myſerye, to honour by dyſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to blyſſynge by curſynge, to reſt &amp; quyetnes by travayll and payne, to ioye and gladnes by wepynge and ſorrowe, to tranquylyte and peace by troubles and af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flictions, to a haven of reſte by a ſtormye tempeſte, to lyffe by deathe, to ſalvation by perylles, to libertye by captyvyte, to lyght by darknes, to ryches by povertye, to contentation by contempte, to amyte by inimyte, to conſolation by dyſſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſaciete and fulnes by hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and nedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to pleaſure by dyſpleaſure, to a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate coldnes by an exceſſyve heate, to glorye by infamye, to a happy ſtate by an vnfortunate meanes. Wherfor as thow haſt now preſent eyperience off thynges aduerſe and troubleſome, even ſo aſſure thy ſelfe off thynges happy &amp; proſperous in tyme to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>The more that I heare thy ſwete ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and comfortable conſolations ſo my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the more do I reſſayve co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentation by theſame. Wherefor blyſſed be thow off the lorde that haſte ſo myche comforted
<pb facs="tcp:185137:20"/>
me. And ſeynge thow doſte ſo frely and largly comonycate thy ſelfe vnto me, I am thereby ſo myche the more boldened to dyſcloſe vnto the all that lyethe in my herte. Thow hardeſt me ſaye even now,<note place="margin">Texte.</note> that the wycked haue aſſauted me all the daye longe, even from my youthe vp, &amp; haue many tymes vexed me, but they coulde neuer as yet ouercome me nor dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troye me. But I now feale my ſelfe greatly debylytated and weakened, as well for that I am waxen decrepyte and aged, as for that my great age ys not ſo prompte and apte to ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſhuche grevous blowes and buffetes, as when I was younge and ſtronge. And yet not withſtandinge the more that I am feabled and and approchynge towardes myn ende, ſo myche the more do they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de me with ſtrypes: ſo that I fere me in the ende I ſhalbe conſtrayned to yelde vp my weapon &amp; armore, and to holde my ſelfe for vanqueſhed. For even as I do declyne to impotencye and feablenes, ſo do myn enymes increaſe in force &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: yea they haue made all redy a wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful breache in my fortreſſe. Truthe it ys, that I haue plenty off monytions: but yf I throuh weaknes cannot vſe them, nor
<pb facs="tcp:185137:21"/>
defende my ſelfe with them, what ſhall they proffyte me? I was wount to haue the greateſte and myghtyeſte on my ſyde, but now god hath taken them awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. There are a great nomber that in the begynynge dyd ſhowe them ſelfes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtoute and manly in my defence:<note place="margin">The Fait herted.</note> But afterwardes wayinge the longe contyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wance off the battayll, and the great da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger off the ſame, they are now vtterly dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courraged, and are become very faynt har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and ferefull. Other ſome are ſo gyven over to voluptiouſnes,<note place="margin">The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines.</note> in the which they are ſo drowned that they ſeke no thynge but to haue peace wyth the enymye, to thende they may wallowe in theyre weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, and remayne in theyre fylthy pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell off fleſhly pleaſure.<note place="margin">The Inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtante Mynded</note> Otherſome throught an inconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lyghtnes haue quy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te abandoned and forſaken me at my nede, &amp; haue vnyted them ſelfes with myn eny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, to take part with them agaynſt me. Otherſome are diſperced here and there who do enforce them ſelfes to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt off theyre power not only to wage battayll agaynſt me,<note place="margin">The Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtes</note> but alſo agaynſte the Papiſtes myn aduerſares.<note place="margin">The Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidiens.</note> Otherſome are as ſpyes to ſpye ont thoſſe that are moſt weake, to werye them: and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewe
<pb facs="tcp:185137:21"/>
the ſtronger, to trouble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that fynaly I ſe none remaine on my ſyde,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> but people condemned to deathe, ſhuche as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re made agaſynge ſtocke vnto the worlde, to the angelles and to men, people that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re become fooles for Chriſtes ſake, and dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piced vnto this tyme, hauynge hounger, thyrſte, and nakednes, beynge buffyted with fyſtes, ſtrayinge from place to place laborynge and workynge with theyre ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne handes: who are revyled, and yet they blyſſe: who are perſecuted, and yet thy ſuffer: who are evell ſpoken of, and yet they praye: yea they are made as it were the fylthynes off the worlde, and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourynge of all thynges, even vntyl this daye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>Truly thow art worthely compared vnto the woman great with chylde,<note place="margin">Apo. 12.</note> who cryethe in travell and ſuffrethe great pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to be delyvered: For the ſerpent dothe moſt cruelly and continewally fyghte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agaynſte thoſſe of thy ſeade that kepe the comau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement off God: and haue the teſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>imonye off Ieſus Chriſte, whom I doute not but that thow loueſte as a mother hyr dere chyldren. But,<note place="margin">4. Eſd. 5. Dani. 12.</note> doeſte thow lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that hathe made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?
<pb facs="tcp:185137:22"/>
Who by that meanes wyll clence pourge and proue them: whether it be by ſworde, by fyre, by captyvite, or by the ſpoyle off theyre goodes for a longe ſeaſon. But now I wyll anſwer particularely to all the complayntes that thow haſte made. Wheras thow allegeſte that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the vp they haue vexed the:<note place="margin">Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3.</note> that ought not to trouble the, ſeyinge that it ys a good thynge to take vp the yoocke of the lorde in youthe,<note place="margin">prou. 22.</note> for ſo waxethe it the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re eaſy in age, for the waye that men are accuſtomed to travell in, in theyre you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, they do not lothe nor refuſe in they<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re age. Wherfor content thy ſelfe with the contynewance of this yoocke, for the lorde wyll not forſake the for ever. And me thynkes that thyne age vs more to thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne avantage then otherwyſſe: For the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thow waxeſte, the better ougheſte thow to be exerſyced in the warre: and the better that thow knoweſte the cautel and ſutteltye of thyne enymes, ſo myche the eaſelyer mayſt thowe ouer come the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the more experyence that a man hathe off fyghtynge, ſo myche the ſonner doth he vanquyſhe his aduerſarye. Which thynge ought not a lytel to encorrage the, and to pull vp a good herte, as one that
<pb facs="tcp:185137:22"/>
hopeth ſhortly to fynyſhe the battayll, ſubdew the enyme, and optayne full vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye. Wherfor ſeynge that this excerſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce off fyghtynge ys appoynted vnto the of the lorde,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> ys it not then thy parte lyke a worthy champion valiantly to ſtryve vn to the ende, for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſtryvethe for a maſtrye ſhalbe crowned, excepte he ſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve lawfullye? They alſo that ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in a race, ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne all, but one berethe awaye the pryce, namly he that perſeuerethe his curſe vnto the ende.<note place="margin">Math. 16.24.</note> For it ys wrytten that he that perſeuereth vnto thende, ſhalbe ſaved. It behovethe the huſband man fyrſte to imploye hys labour, before he taſte off the frutes. Wherfor I thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it not vnmete to put the in remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce off the wordes off thy ſonne Paul ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochynge towardes his ende:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4</note> I am now redy (ſayeth he) to be offred and put to deathe, the tyme off my departynge, ys at hande: I haue fought a good fyghte, I haue fulfylled my curſe, I haue kep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the fayght, from hens forthe there ys layed vp for me a crowne off ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which the lorde (that ys a ryght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe iudge) ſhall gyve me at that daye: not vnto me only, but vnto all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo that love his comynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:185137:23"/>Yea, but thow wareſte very weake (as thow ſayeſte) &amp; thyne enymes incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in ſtrenght?<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.</note> Truly, the aduerſytes off the ryghtouſe are manye, but the lorde delyvereth hym from them all.<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.</note> Ys it not he that ſupporteth thy quarrell agaynſte them that moue warre agaynſte the? Doe the he not take vp the buckler and the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; ryſe vp into thy ſuccour? Doethe he not brynge forthe the ſpere and ſtope the waye agaynſte them that purſewe the?</p>
               <p>Doethe not he confounde &amp; put to ſhame all thoſſe that ſeke after thy ſoul, &amp; image<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evell agaynſt the? Are not all they repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and put to foyle that pretende myſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffe agaynſte the? Doethe not the magnife<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent lorde loue the peace off his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes? Seeſte thow not how that the wycked haue drawen out theyre ſworde, and bent theyre bowe, to caſt downe the poore and nedy, and to ſlaye ſhuche as be off ryght conuerſation: but theyre ſwordes ſhall perce theyre owne herte, &amp; theyre bowe ſhalbe broken? Off theſſe thynges I wyll ſpeke more amply here afterwardes.</p>
               <p>Content thy ſelfe then (with out beynge diſcorraged through thyne age) with the anſwer that was made to Paul, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he prayed vnto the lorde that the angell of
<pb facs="tcp:185137:23"/>
the lorde myght departe from hym: my grace ys ſufficient for the,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12</note> for my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght ys made perfyte through weaknes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the lorde. Wherfor then with that holy apoſtell reioyſe agaynſt thyne aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes in thyne infirmites, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that the ſtrenght off Chriſte thy ſpouce may dwell in the: Take the lyke delectation that he dyd in infyrmytes, in rebukes, in neceſſites, in perſecutions, in anguyſhes for Chriſtes ſake: For when thow ſhalbe ſo weakened, then ſhalt thow be founde ſtrongeſte.</p>
               <p>Fynally wheras thow doeſte bewayll the inconſtant weaknes and wycked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlynes off them that haue forſaken the: Doeth not Ieſus Chriſte ſaye,<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plant that my father hathe not plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhall be pluked vp by the rootes?<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> Doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the he not alſo cut of from the trew vyne (which ys Chriſte) ev<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>y bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che that bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gethe not forthe good frute?<note place="margin">Eſai. 6.</note> Are they not that people that haue theyre hertes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyned, theyre eayres ſtopped, theyre eyes blynded,<note place="margin">Eſai. 8.</note> whom the lorde hathe throwen awaye? All though they aſſemble and conſpyre to gyther, feare them not,<note place="margin">Eſai. 1.</note> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a fearde of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for it ys a ſynful people, a felowſhype off great iniquyte,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:24"/>
a ſede off vngracious chyldren corruptyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge theyre wayes, who haue forſaken the lorde (and not only the) and haue prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the holy one off Iſrael vnto anger, &amp; are gone quyte awaye from hym.<note place="margin">Eſai. 30.</note> Yea they are that rebellious people, whoſſe ſonnes are mortherers, and whoſſe chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren wyll not heare the lawe off the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. But what ſhalbe theyr ende? The ſame prophet declarethe it:<note place="margin">Eſa. 49.</note> therfor ſhall they haue myſcheffe for theyre dyſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and fall lyke as a hyghe wall that fallythe by cauſe off ſome ryfte or blaſte, whoſſe brekynge comethe ſodenly. But off the, it ys ſayd: that thoſſe that ſhall bylde the vp ſhall make haſte, and thoſſe that woulde rewynate and dyſtroye the, ſhalbe expelled fare from the.</p>
               <p>As towchynge that People off En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland which thow lamenteſt ſo myche, bycauſe off the great iniure and ſklande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous offence that they haue commytted agaynſt the:<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note> Suppoſe, Englande to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne off the .vij. heades off that beaſte that ryſſe out off the ſee, which was (as it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re) wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to deathe, &amp; his deadly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de was healed: which wounde was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with that ſworde dyed in bloud, which ys the worde off God, who hathe now
<pb facs="tcp:185137:24"/>
reproued and reiected them, wherin he hath declared his marvelous iudgment But what wrou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hath he done to them,<note place="margin">Eſai. 50.</note> by gyvynge them ſhuche a byll off devorce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, and by puttynge a waye ſhuche a harlott? And who ys the vſerer to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ſolde them? Were they not ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for theyre inyquytes? And was not that wycked ſtrompet forſaken for hyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences? When he cam vnto them: why woulde they not reſſayve hym? When he dyd cal them: why dyd they not anſwer? But yet for all that, ys his hande ſo ſhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tened that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not helpe them? Or hath he not power to delyver them? Beholde all the wycked amongeſte them ſhalbe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto an olde clothe, &amp; the mothe ſhall eate them vp: Cannot the lorde then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them agayne, when it ſhall pleaſe hym? And all though he wyll not do it: what art thow (O peacyble Churche) that ſo myche fereſte mortall man,<note place="margin">Eſai. 54.</note> &amp; the ſonnes off men, who are lyke vnto wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered haye. For even as the lorde dyd cal the beynge as a younge deſolate ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woman, and as a younge wyffe that hathe broken hyr wedlocke, ſo al thoughe for a lytell whyle he do forſake the, yet with great mercyfulnes ſhall he take the
<pb facs="tcp:185137:25"/>
vp gayne: and all though he beynge an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry for a lytell ceaſon do hyde his fate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, yet throught an euerlaſtynge mercye wyll he haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion on the. And hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de this for a ſure certaynte that not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge the inconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mutabilite of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theyre vanite &amp; corruption:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2</note> yet the fyrme fondation of God abydethe parmanant for ever, which hathe this ſeale: the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de knowethe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are his, &amp; let every man that callethe vpon the name of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te depart from iniquyte.</p>
               <p>And fynally to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, as towchynge thoſſe that haue withdrawen them ſelfes from the, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſpacke ſome what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I wyll put the in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of that which.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.</note> S. Iohn ſayde to the longe ago. They went out from the, but they were not of the: for yff they had byne of the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of thyne, they woulde no doute ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewed with the: but they are gone awaye, to thende it myght appere that they were none of thyne:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo it ys neceſſarye that there be ſectes, to thende that thoſſe which are perfyt, may be knowen. But waye the ende, I pray the, of ſhuche offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cive perſons &amp; ſterers vp of ſectes,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> Even as the tares (ſayeth Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte) are gathered &amp; bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:25"/>
ſo ſhall it be in the ende off the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſend forth his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, and they ſhal gather out of his kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thynges that offende, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which do iniquyte, &amp; ſhall caſte them into a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of fyre, &amp; there ſhalbe wepynge and gnaſhynge of teethe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>Truly all that ys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of god is moſt certaine &amp; veritable: for all the wordes of God are pure &amp; cleane &amp; a ſhylde vnto all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that put theyre truſt there in,<note place="margin">prou. 30.</note> yea it ys lyke vnto a fyre that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth all the aſſautes of Sathan:<note place="margin">Iere. 23.</note> and lyke vnto a ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer that breketh the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſtone. And therefor in herynge the ſpeke it ſemethe vnto me that my grevous wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des are eaſed &amp; couled with the moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table playſter of conſolation: And by the power of the worde of God I feale my ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe wonderfully fortyfyed: for thereby, in fyghtyng I am ſuſtayned, in trouble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, in dangers aſſured, in mornynges reioyſed, &amp; in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations protected. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for I wyll fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hens forthe more fyrmely put my truſt in the lorde,<note place="margin">pſal. 37.</note> my delyte ſhalbe all to gyther in hym, I wyll caſte my ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vpon hym, I wyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myte my waye vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the lorde, &amp; put my whol truſte in him:<note place="margin">Iob. 13.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:185137:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And all though he wyll kyll me, yet wyl I ſettel my hope in hym: for I knowe he wylbe my ſalvation. And yet for al that I am wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully invyroned with many grevous afflictions. Namly the plowers haue plowed vpon my backe,<note place="margin">Texte.</note> &amp; haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de longe forrowes: &amp; haue forged vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my backe as yff they had beaten vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyle: in ſhuche ſorte that all thoſſe that pas by me,<note place="margin">Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2.</note> clape theyre ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des at me, hyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge, &amp; waggynge theyre heddes: ſo that this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnt of Eſdras may worthely be appropried vnto me.<note place="margin">4. Eſd. 10</note> Oure ſanctuarye (which ys the pure ſervyce off God) ys now layed waſte:<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.</note> Oure aulter (to wytt Chriſte imolated) ys broken downe: ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple dyſtroyed, &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of idoles: oure ſyngynge of pſalmes (by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſonges) ys layed downe: oure tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes gyvynge (by fals inuocation) ys put to ſylence: oure myrthe (by ſorrowe) ys vanyſhed awaye: the lyght of oure candel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtycke (which ys the worde off God) ys quenched by ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: the arke of oure co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te (by the corrupters of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes) ys taken awaye: oure holy thynges (by the fylthynes of mens traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyled: the name that ys called over vs, ys diſhonored: oure chyldren (for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction)
<pb facs="tcp:185137:26"/>
are put to ſhame: oure mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters of the worde, are brente: oure ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiours &amp; elders are led into captivite: ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vyrgens (by wycked vowes) are defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: oure wyffes (by baalles preſtes) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyſhed: oure ryghtous men, ſpoyled: ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (by naughty educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) diſtroy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>et: oure younge men, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to ſerve ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge godes: and oure ſtronge worthyes haue loſt theyre ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght, &amp; are vtterly fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len awaye from me by the ſuttell perſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions of popyſhe prelates: and that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte ys, it ſemethe that I am vtterly forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp; deſtytuted of my honour, &amp; that God hath delyvered me into the handes of them that hate me. Yet nevertheles for all that I wyll not dyſpayre nor dyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſt in my god, but that he wyl performe in me all that he hath promyſed. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for conſyderynge this my purpoſed inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t founded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy worde of my God: do not hyde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me (O Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolator) thoſſe tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that God hath gyven the:<note place="margin">Math. 23</note> but tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyque &amp; imploye them with me, hopynge that thow ſhalt gayne as many more, to thende that the lorde havynge founde the a fayghtfull ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in a lytell, he may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitute &amp; ſtablyſhe the over myche &amp; ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his reſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:185137:27"/>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>In all theſſe thy tribulations, which thow haſte alleged, thow ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt do no better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtaye thy ſelfe vpon the goodnes &amp; mercye of thy God:<note place="margin">1. cor. 10.</note> who ys fayghtful &amp; wyll not ſuffer the to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted aboue thy ſtrenght, but wyll in the myddes of thy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation make awaye, that thow mayſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te be able to beare it. The which thynge thow haſte all redy ſufficyently experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in that he hath al wayes delyvered the from ſo many enymes, as thow haſt had ſyns the begynynge, beynge ſo ſtronge and myghty,<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> &amp; from ſo many grevous aſſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as they haue made agaynſte the: and therfor it was not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with out a cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, that he that wyll enter into the ſeruy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of God, let hym prepare his ſoul to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation: For the hatred of the perſecuters ys neyther,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> new, nor ſeldom: As Paul one of thy worthy warryours &amp; valiant cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pions hathe ſuffyciently experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, in ſtrypes aboue meaſure, in pryſon ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly, in peryll of deathe often, hauyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge reſſayved of the iewes fyve tymes .xl. ſtrypes lackynge one, beynge thryſſe beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with roddes, ons ſtoned, thryſſe ſuffred ſhypwracke on the ſee, wheron he was nyght &amp; daye, in iorneynge ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in peryl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:185137:27"/>
of robbers, in perylles of his owne na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, in perylles amongeſte the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in perylles in the cyte, in perylles in the wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dernes, in perylles in the ſee, in perylles amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt fals brytheren, in labour &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, in watchynge often, in hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and thyrſte, in faſtynge often, in colde &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: hauynge thorowly taſted that which the lorde Chriſte promyſed hym be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly how grrat thynges it behoued hym to ſuffer for his names ſake.</p>
               <p>Forther more alſo were as thow ſayeſte that the plowers haue plowed vpon thy backe:<note place="margin">Texte.</note> therby thow mayſt vnderſtande that thy perſecuters are called &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to plowmen &amp; laborers for as myche as they do take payne to perſecute the, as do the the laborer to labor, &amp; the plowma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tyll the earthe: which hath byne ever ſyns the begynynge.<note place="margin">Gene. 4.</note> For Cain co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpyryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the deathe of his brother, was not his face altred &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged with diſpleaſure?</p>
               <p>Pharao perſecutynge the people of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell in what payne was he?<note place="margin">Exo. 8 9.10.11.14. 1. reg. 18.</note> Saul afflyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng David, &amp; lokynge ov<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>twharte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, after that he had kylled the Philiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tian: was he not more troubled &amp; vexed then Dauid hym ſelfe?<note place="margin">3 reg. 21, 22.28.</note> In what travell &amp; agonye was Achab perſecutynge Nabot
<pb facs="tcp:185137:28"/>
for his vynyarde, the prophet Elias and Micheas?<note place="margin">Dani. 3.</note> In what affliction &amp; agonye was Nabucodoneſor beholdinge the great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancy of the three young Iſraelytes? was he not all togyther replet with indig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation ſo that the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynance of his face cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged agaynſte them?<note place="margin">2. mac. 9.</note> What happyned there vnto that myſerable Antiochus per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutynge the Iewes, then the people off God, dyd he not fynyſhe his dayes with myſerye &amp; dollor intollerable?<note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>explycable payne &amp; trouble had thoſſe wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked ſcribes &amp; phareſes in purſewynge that moſt innocent, Ieſus Chriſte? And thoſſe alſo that dyd perſecute Stephen,<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> dyd not theyre hertes cleve a ſonder &amp; gnaſhed on hym with theyre teethe?<note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> Herode the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer of Iames perſecutynge the in thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne youthe, was not his wyckednes moſt grevouſly ponyſhed?<note place="margin">Act. 16.</note> Thoſſe alſo that im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſoned Paul &amp; Silas at Philippos, we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re they not more troubled &amp; vexed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that were impriſoned?<note place="margin">Act 12.22.23.</note> What travayll and trouble had the perſecutors of Paul, as well in theyre proces, as in theyre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpyra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces agaynſt hym? And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, in theſſe dayes what payne &amp; trouble haue thyne aduerſares, in all theyre atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryces, ſpyinges, ſerchynges, chaſynges hyther and thyther, commaundynges,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:28"/>
prohybytynges, thretenynges, excomuny catynges, and purſewynges? And there for, in reſpect of the payne that they do ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke, they are iuſtly called plowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: &amp; for the frute of theyre labor there abydethe them no thynge els but eternall da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. In that alſo thow art plowed &amp; labored thow haſt ſome ſimilitude with the earthe, the wich as by plowynge &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borynge it ys pourged &amp; clenſed off all thor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bels &amp; wedes, &amp; afterwardes brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gethe forthe good &amp; pleaſant frute: eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo by afflictions thow art excitated &amp; better diſpoſed to bringe forthe the frute of godly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in pacience. And as many tymes as thow art plowed &amp; harrowed by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Math. 13. Luc. 8. Mat. 4.</note> ſo many thornes &amp; wedes are there taken awaye from the. For this ſede which ys the worde of God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brynge forthe no frute in the: excepte fyrſte theſſe ſtony places be altred and dygged vp with the mattocke of adv<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ſyte: the thornes that ſo miche checke the worde of god torned vp by the ploughe of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that harde hyghe waye labored with the harrow off affliction: For otherwyſſe the good ſede that that ys ſowen therin wylbe come vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnprofytable &amp; eaten vp of ravens. But thow beyinge thorowly tylled &amp; labo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, art not altogyther vnlyke thy ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce
<pb facs="tcp:185137:29"/>
Ieſus Chrlſte of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ys ſayed. That he hath trodden the vyne preſſe alone,<note place="margin">Eſa. 63.</note> &amp; there was no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to helpe hym. Forther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>more thow mayſt evyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly perſayde that thy perſecutors thynkynge to do the great hurte, they do the myche good: al though they beat vpon thy backe as vpon an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, yet can they no more hurte the with theyre ſtrypes, then the ſmyte hurtethe the anvyle with his hamer.<note place="margin">Texte.</note> I perſayve al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo that the longe laſtynge of thy perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſignyfyed by the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge forrowes, dothe not a lytell anoye the &amp; ſemeth vnto the very tedious &amp; lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: But be of good chere, &amp; aſſure thy ſelfe that the ende of all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges approcheth &amp; drawethe nye.<note place="margin">2. pet. 3.</note> For this ys the laſt tyme. But thow mayſte not be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of this, that a daye with the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ys as a thowſande yere, &amp; a thowſand yere as a daye: the lorde ys not ſlacke in his promes, as the perſecuters exteme ſlac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knes: but ys pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to wardes all, in that he woulde haue no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loſte, but woulde haue al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> torne to repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And let this ſuffice the, that thyne enymes do no thynge els, but haſten &amp; prycke the forwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to the comynge of the daye of the lorde: wherfor marke this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wel which ys wrytten.<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.</note> The tyme ys at hande, that he
<pb facs="tcp:185137:29"/>
that dothe evell, let hym do evell ſtyll, &amp; he which ys fylthy let hym be fylthy ſtyll: &amp; he that ys ryghtous, let hym be more ryghtous, &amp; he that ys holy, let hym be more holy: for beholde I come ſhortly, &amp; my rewarde with me, to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordynge to his dedes.<note place="margin">Texte. Hebr. 6.</note> For the lorde whoſe thow art, &amp; who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thow ſerveſte, ys iuſte, he wyll not forgett thy worke &amp; thy labor.<note place="margin">Texte. Hebr 13. Ioſua. 1.</note> He hathe all redy cut in ſonder the cordes of the wycked. And hath ſayed I wyll not forſake the, neyther wyll I aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the. So that thow mayſt ſurely ſaye: the lorde ys my helper.<note place="margin">pſal. 118. Hebr. 10.</note> I fere not what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can do vnto me. Tary a lytell whyll &amp; he that ſhall come, wyll come &amp; wyll not ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, who cuttynge a ſonder the cordes off thy perſecutors, wyll render vnto them as they haue done vnto the, &amp; wyll rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> double accordynge to theyre dedes. And into the ſame cuppe which they haue fylled vnto the,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> the lorde wyll power in double: And loke how myche they gloryed in them ſelfes, &amp; toke pleaſure to afflicte the, ſo myche ſhall there be gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; teares. And this ys it that one of thy prophetes ſpekynge vnto the in the name of God, ſayethe:<note place="margin">Eſai. 51.</note> O thow myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken, but not with wyne, heare
<pb facs="tcp:185137:30"/>
this, thus ſayethe the lorde: thy lorde and god, the defender of his people: Beholde I haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſlu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brynge cuppe out of thy hande, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cuppe with the dregges off my wrathe: &amp; that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hens forthe thow ſhalt nev<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> dryncke it more: but I wyll put it into theyre handes that trouble &amp; vexe the. So that it ys appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here by, that they haue more occaſion to wepe &amp; way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thow. The which thynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of Ieſꝰ Chriſte goynge vnto his dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the, moved hym to ſaye vnto the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that followed mournynge af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter hym.<note place="margin">Luc. 23.</note> O ye dawghters of Ieruſalem, wepe not for me, but wepe for your ſelfes &amp; for your chyldren: for yf they haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne this vnto grene wood, what ſhall the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be done vnto the drye?<note place="margin">prou. 11.</note> Beholde ſayeth the wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the iuſte ſhalbe ponyſhed yf he do wyckedly in the earthe, how myche more then the vngodly &amp; ſynner? Where vnto ys to be refarred the ſaynge of the lorde by the mouthe of his prophet.<note place="margin">Iere. 25.</note> Yff I begyne to plage that cyte (ſayeth the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de) where vnto my name ys gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I wyl leave ye vnponyſhed? Ye ſhall not go quyte,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.</note> but wyl cauſe your tribulation to fall vpon your owne hedd. For truly the wycked ys kepte for the day
<pb facs="tcp:185137:30"/>
off dyſtruction, and the vngodly ſhalbe brought forthe in the daye of wrathe.</p>
               <p>Thow ſayeſt that they haue plowed &amp; harrowed the, well let them alſo prepare theire ſythes, for the harveſte ys rype:<note place="margin">Ioel. 3.</note> let them come and gett them downe, for the wynepreſſe ys full: Yea the wynepreſſe ronnethe ouer, for theyre wyckednes ys waxen greate: What reſtethe now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that the angell of the lorde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Apocalypes,<note place="margin">Apoc. 14</note> do thruſte in his ſharpe ſyckell into the earthe, &amp; gather the cluſters of the vynes of the earthe, for hir grapes are rype, &amp; caſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the great wyne fatt of the wrathe of god: who bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gethe marvelous thynges to pas, who forſeethe the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayll of the wycked,<note place="margin">Eſa. 25.</note> and ſtablyſheth thynges certayne. For it ys he, that ys the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght of the poore, &amp; the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cor of the nedy in his trouble: A refuge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte foul weather, &amp; a ſhadowe agayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte the heate: It ys he that ſuppreſſethe the noyſe of the wycked infideles, as the heate in a drye place, &amp; bryngethe low the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che of the myghty, as the heate in the ſhadow of the cloude: And the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors ſhalbe trodden downe vnder hym,<note place="margin">Iere. 49.</note> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed to peces, as ſtrawe in a dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hyll. For beholde they that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought vnmete to dryncke of the cuppe, haue taſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:185137:31"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:185137:31"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:185137:32"/>
of it with the fyrſte, &amp; ſhall the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the thynke to eſcape fre? No, for eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they haue done to the, ſo ſhall it be done to them agayne.<note place="margin">Eſai. 63.</note> Thow ſhalt be as the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; thy chyldren as the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, &amp; thy per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutors ſhalbe as the ſtrawe. For the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de wyll tread them downe in his wrathe, &amp; bathe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theyre owne bloude in his diſpleaſure: &amp; beat downe theyre ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earthe, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume them in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of hid indignation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 33.</note>But as for the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thow art moſt happy (O Churche) who ys lyke vnto the? for thow art ſaved in the lorde, which ys the ſhylde off thy helpe, &amp; the ſworde off thy glorye: thyne enymes ſhall loſſe theyre ſtrenght to the warde, &amp; thow ſhalt tread vpon the hygheſt of them, This ys the iuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyce of thy God,<note place="margin">Eſai. 66.</note> &amp; the pacience of Saync<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, who in the ende ſhall reioyſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the wycked ſhalbe confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: Then thy chyldren ſhall ſynge for ioye of herte, and thy perſecutors ſhall crye through ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe off mynde, &amp; ſhall howle through dyſquyetnes of ſpirete, &amp; ſhall leve theyre name for execration vnto the elect of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>Truly thow haſte greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted me, &amp; haſte ſpoken very lovyngly vnto me:<note place="margin">Ruth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</note> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:185137:32"/>
haſt ſufficyently ſatiſfyed all my demaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des: not doubtinge but that throught the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſe conſolations off the ſcryptures which thow haſt alleged, I ſhall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hens forthe be greatly fortyfyed in all my tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when as the glory of God ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre the ſame: And ſeynge that he ys my helper,<note place="margin">Eſai. 50.</note> I am ſure I ſhall not be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: &amp; all though my face be hardened ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a a flynt ſtone in the fyre, yet am I cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne I ſhall not come to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion: for he that wyll iuſtifye me, ys at hande: who wyll the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go to the lawe with me? Let myn adv<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ſarye come forthe now &amp; pleat agayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte me, for the lorde ſhall heare my cauſe. Beholde the lorde ſtandethe by me, what ys he then that ſhal conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne me?<note place="margin">Eſai. 51.</note> I do not fere the curſe of men: I am not afferde of theyre blaſphemes and reuelynges: for mothes ſhall eate them vp lyke clothe, &amp; wormes ſhall devoure them lyke wooll.</p>
               <p>Yet would I fayne haue forther inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the iſſew &amp; fynal ende of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly myne aduerſares, all though thow ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte partly all redy towched the ſame. For what? Shall they floryſhe any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynewa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before theyre floure fall? Shall theyre glorye laſt for ever with out beyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge throwen downe? Shall they all wayes
<pb facs="tcp:185137:33"/>
haue the vpper hande? Shall they not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne daye be brought vnder? Theyre crual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, ſhall it not ceaſe, ſo that they ſhal no more ſhead the bloude of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall the impoſtumation of theyre corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hertes breke a ſonder? Shall not the dregges of theyre pryde be ſhortly preſſed out, ſo that the fylthynes thereof may ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pere? Shall the floure of theyre vanyte laſte lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge with out wytherynge &amp; corrupti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on? Ys the tyme longe before theyre gren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be dryed vp, to thende they may be caſt into the fyre and bornte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Conſolator.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 34.</note>The eare provethe &amp; deſerueth the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des: &amp; the mouthe taſteth the meate. I am glade that the lorde hathe gyven me a tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, to expreſſe in tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venyent the worde of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation to hyr that ys vexed &amp; afflycted.<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.</note> I haue all redy declared vnto the, how that thy chyldren haue byn rac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; beaten &amp; woulde not be delyvered: how that otherſome were tryed with ſkor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynges &amp; mockynges, with bondes &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: other were ſtoned, were hewen a ſunder, were te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, were ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne with ſworde, walked vp &amp; downe in ſhepſkins &amp; gotſkins, beynge deſtitute, troubled &amp; vexed, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worlde was
<pb facs="tcp:185137:33"/>
not worthy of: whoſſe enymes are alſo peryſhed, as though they never had byn. But theſſe are ryghtous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſſe ryght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes ſhall nev<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Eccl. 44.</note> whoſſe chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren &amp; glorye ſhall never be forſaken, they<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re bodeys are buryed in peace, but theyre name lyvethe for ever, the people ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> talke of theyre wyſdome, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeke of theyre prayſe: for it was requyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te that (with out any excuſſe) diſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſſe that vſed tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nye,<note place="margin">Sapi. 16.</note> wherby they myght leve an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple vnto men as a memoryall of theyre follye, &amp; to ſhowe vnto other, how theyre enymes were dyſtroyed.<note place="margin">Sapi. 17.</note> For when the vnryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thynke to haue thy holy people in ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection, then ſhall they be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with the bondes of darknes &amp; longe nyght, &amp; cut in peces:<note place="margin">Sapi. 3.</note> But the ſoules of the ryghtous are in the handes of God, &amp; the payne of dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the ſhall not towche them: in the eyes of the vnryghtous they ſhall ſeme to dye, &amp; theyre ende to be very dyſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but they reſt in peace, &amp; all though they ſuffer pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne before men, yet ys theyre hope full off i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mortalite: they are ponyſhed but in few thynges, never the les in many thynges ſhall they be well rewarded,<note place="margin">Eccle 32.</note> for God pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vethe them &amp; fyndethe them mete for him
<pb facs="tcp:185137:34"/>
ſelfe. As evell ys all wayes agaynſt good, &amp; deathe agaynſte lyffe, ſo ys the vngodly agaynſte ſhuche as fere God, the ſynner agaynſte the ryghtous, &amp; the perſecuter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the fayghtfull: but in the ende god wyll breke the hedd off the enymes, who ſaye,<note place="margin">Texte.</note> there are none but we. Not witſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng for thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation it ys ſayed, that ſhuche as hate the ſhall be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; put to ſilence.<note place="margin">pſal 73. Eſa. 29.</note> And that not with out a cauſe, for they are ſet in ſlypry places &amp; God wyl make them fall into dyſtruction. For eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he that ys hongrye, dremethe that he ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth, but when he a wakethe his ſoule ys emptye, &amp; as he that ys thurſtye dremethe that he drynkethe, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he awakethe, he ys faynte, &amp; his ſoule hathe appetyte: even ſo ſhall it be to the multitude off all thoſſe nations that fyght agaynſte the. For thoſſe that do the hurte ſhalbe extermy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:<note place="margin">pſal. 37.</note> &amp; it ſhall come to pas ſhortly that the vngodly ſhall haue no more place. They ſhal peryſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumynge as the fatt of a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be, &amp; vanyſhe awaye as ſhe ſmoke. Tary the lordes leaſure &amp; thow ſhalt ſe the dyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruction of the wycked: who all though they haue ſome tyme floryſhed as the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne lawryell, yet ſo ys it that they paſſynge a lytell forther ſhalbe no more fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, for
<pb facs="tcp:185137:34"/>
theyr laſt rewarde ys dyſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the lorde wyl plucke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp as vntymely gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vyne,<note place="margin">Iob. 15.</note> &amp; ſhal let theyre flower fall as dothe the olyve tre, yea they ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be as chaffe before the wynde, &amp; as duſte that the horſe wynde blowethe awaye. The which thynge ys more amplye expre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſed in thoſe wordes which I reſyted vnto the before, to wytt,<note place="margin">Texte.</note> They ſhalbe as the gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſe that groweth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the howſe toppes, which wythereth a fore it be plucked vp. Beholde thys ys the ende of the labor off the vngodly, &amp; theyre wyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ynges, for all theyre lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge forrowes, toyle, &amp; payne: for al that ſhall profyte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greſſe that growethe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the howſſe top<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe: yea, &amp; they them ſelfes ſhalbe cut dow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne as haye, &amp; ſhall drye awaye as grene greſſe. So happyned it vnto Senacherib,<note place="margin">Eſa. 35. 4. reg. 19.</note> perſecutynge the Churche of of Iſrael in the dayes of Eſaias &amp; Ezechias, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſſe wordes are ſpoken, as of all other thy perſecutors: Shuche as ys the ſede of the wycked, ſhuche ys theyre harveſte.</p>
               <p>He that ſoweth in the fleſhe,<note place="margin">Gala. 6.</note> ſhal alſo of the fleſhe reape corruption: But of the &amp; thyne which ſowe in teares, it ys ſayd, that ye ſhal reape in ioye.<note place="margin">pſal. 126.</note> They we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te (ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the pſalmiſte) on theyre waye we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:35"/>
berynge forthe theyre ſede, butt doutles they ſhal come agayne with ioye &amp; brynge theyre ſheaues with them. But it ſhall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywyſſe vnto the wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked, for they ſowe in ioye, but they ſhall reape in teares:<note place="margin">Texte.</note> for of theire ſede the mow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er fylleth not his hande, nor the glener his boſome.<note place="margin">Iob. 24.</note> And why? For they ſpoyle the ſuckynge fatherles chylde, &amp; take the pledge from the poore, ſo that they let hym go naked with out clothynge, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue taken awaye the ſheave of the houn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye: ys it any mervell then yff theyr ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ave be with out frute? ſeynge that they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue violated &amp; taken awaye the ſheave of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?<note place="margin">Eccle. 8.</note> The preacher noteth one goodly ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, By cauſe (ſayeth he) that evell workes are not forth with ponyſhed in the workers, therfor the herte of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth hym ſelfe vnto wyckednes: for all though an evell perſon offende an houn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth tymes, &amp; god defarre, gyvinge him lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lyffe: yet am I ſure that it ſhall go well with them that fere God, by cauſe they haue him before theyr eyes: as for the vngodly it ſhal not be wel with hym, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſhall he prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hys dayes? but even as a ſhadowe ſo ſhall he be that fereth not God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:185137:35"/>To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude all the labor of the wycked &amp; vngodly tendeth to no thynge els,<note place="margin">Eccle. 10.</note> but to afflicte them ſelfes: in as myche as the ſheave of theyre labor dothe not fyll they<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hande. And yf the mowers do fynde no thynge that ys valuable,<note place="margin">pſal. 1.</note> the gleayners nede not to go after them, to hope to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any goodnes. For how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de any good thynge, when as they are as chaffe, which the wynde bloweth away<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>e? Theyr vayne atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes are wel expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the prophet, wheras he ſayethe:<note place="margin">Eſa. 17.</note> They ſhalbe chaſed awaye lyke as drye ſtrawe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines before the wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, &amp; lyke as a thynge that torneth before the ſtorme: at eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beholde there ys trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; or ev<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> it be mornynge beholde it ys go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. And this ys it that Iohn baptyſte me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayed, that god hath his fanne in his hande, &amp; wyll purge his flower, &amp; ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther his wheate into his barne, but wil borne the chaffe with vnque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheable fyre. For the wycked ſhalbe beaten as ſmal as duſte before the wynde,<note place="margin">pſa. 18.</note> &amp; ſhalbe caſte for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th as the dyrte in the ſtretes: And theyr hope ſhall melte awaye as the wynter,<note place="margin">Sapi. 18.</note> &amp; rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e awaye as a ſwyfte water ſtreme in the ryv<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>. By theſſe &amp; ſhuche other ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des the ſcriptures dothe declare vnto the,
<pb facs="tcp:185137:36"/>
that the enterpryſes of the wycked are vai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne &amp; nyghe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion,<note place="margin">2. theſſe. 2.</note> to thende that all thoſſe myght be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned that beleved not the truthe, but had pleaſure in vnryghtouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">Pſa, 37.</note> Yea they are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ryſe vp agai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne: ſo that they which go by, ſaye not ſo myche as the lorde proſper you,<note place="margin">Texte.</note> we wyſhe you good lucke in the name of the lorde. Who are the goars by, but the lyvynge? What good ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſaye of that, werof the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re cometh no goodnes? Who wyll prayſe that, that god hathe diſprayſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what good lucke ſhal any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyſhe vnto a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that ys ſo wycked? what ſhal oure blyſſinge pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vayl in that thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, that god hath curſed? who wyll reioyſe in the facte of a morthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer? who wyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gratulate a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth bloude, which thynge requyreth ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; no blyſſyng? who wyl allowe a tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but only ſhuche as thurſte the bloud of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes?<note place="margin">An obiec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. Math. 5. Rom. 12.</note> what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Ys it for nought that Chriſte hath ſaied, blyſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe you, do good the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hatt you? And do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the not one of his apoſtels ſaye as myche? Speke wel of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that perſecute you, bly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but curſe not? Lykewyſſe a nother ſayeth:<note place="margin">1. pet. 3.</note> Render not evel for evel, nor ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for malediction, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſe blyſſe, knowynge that you are there
<pb facs="tcp:185137:36"/>
vnto called, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to poceſſe the herytage of bliſſynge. Or els? The faightful are not they the by goers, &amp; paſſers by thoſſe wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked workmen, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſpack eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now. How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agreethe this doctryne of Ieſus Chriſte &amp; his apoſtles with the doctryne of the pſalmiſte &amp; the prophetes before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited, the one forbiddinge vs to blyſſe the vngodly, &amp; the other coma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge to blyſſe the?<note place="margin">An Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Vve maij praie for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion of the tirra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t jf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it do not evi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly appere that he is the reprobat of God For vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vve are forbidd to praie. 1 Ioh. 5.</note> Truly Ieſus Chriſte nor yet his apoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les do coma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de no thynge agaynſte the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne of the prophetes: for God hath all wayes wylled, &amp; yet wylleth, that al tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſe that are his, do blyſſe, love &amp; praye for theyr perſecutors. But it ys a nother thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge to praye for the perſecutors: and for the perſecution. What godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ys the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re that woulde pray for the good ſucceſſe of any wyckednes? we muſt praye for the tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; not for his tyrra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nye, but rather for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion. And this ys it that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayed. Lorde haue I not hated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that haue hated the? &amp; am not I greued with thoſſe that ryſſe vp againſt the? yea,<note place="margin">pſal. 139.</note> I haue hated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a perfytt hatred, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as though they were myne enimes. But this hatred how veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo ever it be, yet doeth it not hynder the faightfull to do good vnto the vngodly, as
<pb facs="tcp:185137:37"/>
lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as it ſhal pleaſe the lorde to permye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuccorynge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that thynge which they haue of god, to wytt, in the body for, ſeynge that god doeth not as yet with drawe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his benevole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: who ſo ev<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> wyll reſemble hym, muſt not alſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe his. But in that thynge wherin they are lyke vnto Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in theyre lyffe &amp; naughty ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners, in theyr enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſes &amp; iniquites, they muſt be abhorred &amp; deteſted as a peſtele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with out wyſhyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge wel vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by any meanes. There re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge els vnto thoſſe that ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the bloud of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes but maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, execratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; curſynge, as it hath byn ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently declared vnto the here before. Wherin thow mayſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrme thy ſelfe in pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in abydynge the comi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of thy ſpouce, who wyll come ſhortly, and wyll not tarry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The Churche.</speaker>
               <p>¶ I haue diligently noted all thy wordes, which ſeme vnto me mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſweter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> The lorde my god who hathe coma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the lyght to ſhyne out off darknes, knowynge thynges that are not, as yf they were: which hathe ſhyned in oure hertes to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de we may reſſayve the lyght of the knowlege of his glorye in the face of Ieſꝰ Chriſte: accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to his great
<pb facs="tcp:185137:37"/>
mercye &amp; infinite bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tye replenyſhe me, with all ſtrenght, conſtancye, corrage &amp; pacience in my tribulations: gyvynge me an invyncible herte interely to abhere &amp; cleve vnto hym: to ſettel &amp; ſtaye my ſelfe in his promyſſes: to fere &amp; reuerence his thretenynges, &amp; to avaunce the kyngdom and glorye of his ſonne. And forther that it wyll pleaſe hym to publyſhe &amp; manifeſte his goſpell every where, &amp; his god wyll to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes al people, ſo that the darknes off ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye may be vniuerſally expelled, by the comynge of his bryghtnes: and that all ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſecutors may be reduced to the ryght waye of ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ceaſyng <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re tyrra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nye &amp; perſecution. <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I do vndoutedly beleue, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege that the lorde god <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the caſtel, the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thoſſe that p<gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> who ys Go<gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge but <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wayed <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> me, <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſla<gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> me <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pl<gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: torn page" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:185137:38"/>
for we are his, whether it be in lyffe or deathe. Onely we beſeche him that he wil not leave vs, nor forſake vs, but that we may perfytly ſerve hym, to the forthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his glorye, &amp; the exaultation of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gdome of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, who lyveth with hym &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly goſte in eternall felicyte: to whom be prayſe for ever and ever. So be it.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
